A Finding Aid to the W.G. Constable Papers, 1905-1983, bulk 1920-1976, in the Archives of American Art AAA.conswmgp
Archives of American Art
- Correspondence, 1906-1981; Series 2; 6.2 Linear feet Box 2-8, OV 28-29
  - General, 1906-1975; 2.1
    - U Miscellaneous, circa 1940-1960 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - U.S. Treasury Department, Internal Revenue Service, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 69-71)
    - University College London, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - University of Auckland, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - University of New Brunswick, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - University Press Cambridge, 1937-1943 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - V Miscellaneous, circa 1940-1960 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Vasalle, Rudolph A., 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
    - Vassar College (McCormick, Thomas), 1964-1969 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, 1961-1964 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - W Miscellaneous, circa 1940-1960 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Wadsworth Atheneum, 1960-1967 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Wallace Collection, 1924-1968 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Windsor Art Association, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Winterthur Museum (Richardson, E.P. and Harris, Paul S.), 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Witt, John, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Y-Z Miscellaneous, circa 1940-1960 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Unknown and Illegible, circa 1940-1960 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      Oversized material housed in OV 29.
    - Oversize Cartoon, Unknown and Illegible, circa 1940-1960 (Box OV 29)
      Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 17.
  - Committees, 1924-1976; 2.2
    Correspondence includes letters, memoranda, and reports related to ongoing committee objectives, projects, and routine activities. This sub-series also includes correspondence, updates, and recommendations related to Constable's advisory work with the Art Gallery of Toronto, Beaverbrook Art Gallery, National Gallery of Canada, and the Watts Gallery.
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1940-1970 (Box 5, Folder 18-21)
    - American Committee for the Restoration of Italian Monuments, Inc., 1946-1948 (Box 5, Folder 22-25)
    - American Council of Learned Societies, 1948-1949 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - American Federation of the Arts, 1956-1965 (Box 5, Folder 27-31)
    - American Federation of the Arts, 1970-1974 (Box 5, Folder 32-35)
    - Beaverbrook Art Gallery, 1958-1961 (Box 5, Folder 36-37)
    - Art Gallery of Toronto, 1957-1963 (Box 5, Folder 38-41)
      Oversized material housed in Box 28, Folder 2.
    - British Council, 1957-1974 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Brooks Memorial Art Gallery, 1960-1963 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - College Art Association of America, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Comite International D'Histoire de L'Art, 1930-1939 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Comite International D'Histoire de L'Art, 1942-1956 (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
    - Comite International D'Histoire de L'Art, 1957-1966 (Box 6, Folder 5-8)
    - Committee for International Cultural Exchange, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Committee of the Iconographical Commission of the International Committee of Historical Sciences, 1934-1965 (Box 6, Folder 10-11)
    - Committee to Rescue Italian Art, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 12-15)
    - Conference on Science, Philosophy and Religion (Nef, John U.), circa 1940-1963 (Box 6, Folder 16-18)
    - Design and Industries Association, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Exploratory Conference on Conservation, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 20-21)
    - Fine Arts Committee People-to-People Program, 1956-1962 (Box 6, Folder 22-23)
    - International Institute for the Conservation of Museum Objects, 1958-1960 (Box 6, Folder 24-28)
    - Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery, 1947-1950 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - International Council for Philosophy and Humanistic Studies, 1955-1957 (Box 6, Folder 30-34)
    - International Council for Philosophy and Humanistic Studies, 1958-1959 (Box 6, Folder 35-36)
    - International Council for Philosophy and Humanistic Studies, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - International Council of Museums, circa 1940-1960 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - International Institute for the Conservation of Museum Objects, 1947-1961 (Box 7, Folder 3-6)
    - International Institute for the Conservation of Museum Objects, 1962-1966, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 7-10)
    - Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum, 1924, 1940-1948 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Lady Lever Art Gallery, 1947, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 12-13)
    - Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, 1937-1958 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - National Cathedral Association, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - National Gallery of Canada, Ottawa (General), 1933, 1955-1961 (Box 7, Folder 16-21)
    - National Gallery of Canada, Ottawa (Museum Training Course), 1933, 1946, 1958-1960 (Box 7, Folder 22-27)
    - New Brunswick Museum, 1958-1961 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Renaissance Society of America, circa 1940-1959 (Box 7, Folder 29-32)
    - Renaissance Society of America, 1960-1963 (Box 7, Folder 33-36)
    - Renaissance Society of America, 1964-1965 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - Walker Art Center, 1944-1948 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Watts Gallery, 1950-1966 (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
    - Oversize Blueprints, Beaverbrook Art Gallery, 1958 (Box OV 29)
      Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 37.
    - Oversize Financial Chart, Art Gallery of Toronto, 1959 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 39.
    - Oversize Photographs of Artwork, National Gallery of Canada, Ottawa, 1958-1960 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      Oversized material from Box 7, Folder 25.
  - Condolences, 1976-1979; 2.3
    Correspondence consists of letters and cards from friends and family sent to Constable's wife, Olivia, after Constable's death in 1976.
    - List of Correspondents, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - A-C Miscellaneous, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 7-9)
    - C Miscellaneous, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Constable, Olivia, 1976-1979 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - D-H Miscellaneous, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 11-13)
    - I-P Miscellaneous, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 14-16)
    - Q-Z Miscellaneous, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 17-19)
  - J.G. Links, 1964-1981; 2.4
    Correspondence is between J.G. Links and Constable regarding the first edition of Constable's Canaletto, as well as proposed edits and changes to the second edition of the book.
    - Canaletto Research, 1964-1981 (Box 8, Folder 20-22)
- Lectures, 1909-1963; Series 3; 4.6 Linear feet Box 8-12
  Found here are over 170 drafts of Constable's lectures, and supporting notes and outlines. Topics range from surveys of 13th-20th century European and American art to museum conservation, ethics, art education, art collecting, and connoisseurship. There are numerous lectures on English and Italian painting, in addition to lectures on German, French, and American painting traditions. A handful of lectures on individual artists such as John Constable, Joseph Turner, Richard Wilson, Rubens, and Valasquez can also be found. The series also includes Constable's lecture notes from organized touring trips to Canada, Northern Europe, Scandanavia, and Poland.
  Lectures are arranged in alpha order by title.
  - Lecture Announcements, 1935-1936 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Lecture Slide Lists, circa 1930-1950 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Lecture Tour, Canada, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Lecture Tour, Northern Europe, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Lecture Tour, Scandinavia, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Lecture Trip, Poland, 1957, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - "13th and 14th Century French and English Illuminated Manuscripts" (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - "18th Century Art Themes with Special Reference to Landscapes", circa 1930-1950 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - "18th Century Painting, France" (Lecture 1-2), circa 1930-1950 (Box 8, Folder 31-32)
  - "18th Century Painting, France" (from 2 lectures), circa 1930-1950 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - "18th Century English Painting", circa 1930-1958 (Box 8, Folder 34-36)
  - "18th Century English Painting, Watercolors, Later Portraits", circa 1930-1950 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - "18th Century English Portrait Painters", 1945 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - "19th Century French Painting" (Lecture 1-2), circa 1930-1950 (Box 8, Folder 39-40)
  - "19th Century Painting, Landscapes in England", circa 1930-1950 (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - "Art and Academic Study," University of Western Ontario, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - "Art and Democracy," The Club, 1941 (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - "Art and Everyday Life", circa 1930-1950 (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - "Art and Geographical Influences," Oxford, circa 1930-1950 (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - "Art and Social Welfare", 1946 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - "Art Galleries and Museums in Soviet Russia", 1937 (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - "Art Galleries and Social Welfare," Leicester, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 48)
  - "Art History and Academic Study", 1948, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "Art History as a Subject of Academic Study", 1933 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "Art in the Service of Religion," Duke University, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - "Art, Its Place in a Changing World", 1942 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - "Art Museums in the U.S." (radio program), 1947 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - "Art Schools and Community", 1934-1935 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - "Artistic Relations of England and Italy, Middle Ages, Tudor", 1937 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - "Artistic Relations of England and Italy, 17th Century" (Lecture I and II), circa 1930-1950 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - "Artistic Relations of England and Italy, 17th Century" (Lecture III-IV), circa 1930-1950 (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
  - "Artistic Relations of England and Italy, 17th Century", 1952, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - "Arts in a Changing World," Ohio State, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - "Arts in Boston", circa 1930-1950 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - "Arts in Education", circa 1930-1950 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - "Arts in the USA", circa 1930-1950 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - "Importance of Art in Life and Function of Art School", 1942 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - "Canaletto", circa 1930-1950 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - "Care of Paintings," Boston School of Architecture, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - "Collecting for a Museum", circa 1930-1950 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - "Collecting in the U.S." (Lecture I-II), circa 1930-1950 (Box 9, Folder 20-21)
  - "Collecting with Karolik", 1952 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - "Collectors and Collecting" (early version), circa 1930-1950 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - "Collectors and Collecting", 1958, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Commencement Speech, Rhode Island School of Design, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - "Conservation and Reconstruction in Poland", 1958 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - "Curator as Collector", circa 1930-1960 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - "Education in the Arts as an Element in the Integration of Human Culture", 1946 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - "El Greco and Velazquez", 1935 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - "English Art, 19th and 20th Century, Constable to Bacon", 1962 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - "English Conversation Pieces", 1948 (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - "English Dilettanti and Art Collectors", 1937 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - "English Landscape in Poetry and Painting", circa 1950-1960 (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - "English Medieval Painting", 1934 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - "English Medieval Painting, 7th Century - 1250" (Lecture I), circa 1930-1950 (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - "English Medieval Painting, 1250-1350" (Lecture II), circa 1930-1950 (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - "English Medieval Painting, 1350-1480" (Lecture III), circa 1930-1950 (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - "English Medieval Painting, 1480-1600" (Lecture IV), circa 1930-1950 (Box 9, Folder 38)
  - "English Painting and English Life, 1700-1850", 1963 (Box 9, Folder 39)
  - "English Painting, 1900-1950", 1950-1951 (Box 9, Folder 40)
  - "English Patrons and Italian Painters" (Lecture I), circa 1930-1950 (Box 9, Folder 41)
  - "English Patrons and Italian Painters" (Lecture II), circa 1920-1950 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - "English Watercolors", 1945, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - "Ethics for Museum Men," Fogg Art Museum, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - "European Museums and Impressions of Europe", 1947 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - "Examination of Pictures", 1944 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - "French Painting, 1400-1900", circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - "German Problem", 1950 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - "Goya", circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - "Growth of the British Labour Party", 1946 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - "Humanism and Art", circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - "Impressionism and Post-Impressionism", 1945 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - "Influence of Constable and Turner on Landscape Painting in Europe", circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - "Influence of Italy on 17th and 18th Century English Architecture", circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - "International Cooperation and Conservation", circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - "Italian Art in Time of Dante" (Lecture I-III), circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 15-17)
  - "Italian Art in Time of Dante" (Lecture IV-VI), circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 18-20)
  - "Italian Baroque Painting", 1945-1946 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - "Italian Landscape Painting" (Lecture I-II), circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 22-23)
  - "Italian Landscape Painting, 18th Century" (Lecture III-IV), circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 24-25)
  - "Italian Landscape Painting, 18th Century Influence on English Painting" (Lecture V), circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - "Italian Painting, 13th Century", circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - "Italian Painting, 13th Century and 14th Century", circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - "Italian Painting, 18th Century", circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 29-30)
  - "Italian Painting, Fra Angelico, Fra Lippi, Botticelli", circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - "Italian Painting, High Renaissance, Da Vinci", circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - "Italian Painting, High Renaissance, Michaelangelo", circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - "Italian Painting, High Renaissance, Raphael", circa 1930-1950 (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - "Italian Painting, High Renaissance, Giorgione and Titian", circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - "Italian Painting, Mantegna, Bellini, and Tura", circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "Italian Painting, Piero Della Francesca and Signorelli", circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - "Italian Painting, Tintoretto and Veronese", circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "Italian Painting, Uccello, Veneziano, del Castagno", circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - "John Constable", circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - "Joseph M.W. Turner", 1954-1955 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - "Karl Baedeker", 1953 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - "Landscapes, East and West", 1945 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - "Lowell Institute Lectures" (I-IV), circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 10-13)
  - "Lowell Institute Lectures " (V-VIII), circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 14-17)
  - "Luxury and the Economic State", 1909 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - "Mantegna and Humanism in Fifteenth Century Italy", 1937 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - "Masterpieces of 18th Century Painting and Sculpture", circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - "Medieval Painting, Introduciton, Romanesque" (Lecture I), circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - "Medieval Painting, England" (Lecture II), circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - "Medieval Painting, France" (Lecture III), circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - "Medieval Painting, Early Flemish" (Lecture IV), circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - "Medieval Painting, Netherlands, 15th Century" (Lecture V), circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - "Medieval Paintings" (Lecture VI), circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - "Morality and Art," Smith, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - "Mural Painting in England, 17th and 18th Century" (Lecture I-II), circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 28-29)
  - "Museum Acquisitions," Fogg Art Museum, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - "Museum Problems", circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - "Museums and Contemporary Art", circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - "Museums of the Future," Fogg Art Museum, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 33)
  - "National Gallery of Canada and Its Work", circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 34)
  - "New Art and Old Morals," Institute of Religion and Social Studies, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 35)
  - "Old Master Drawings," Bristol University, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - "Painter's Workshop", circa 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 37)
  - "Painting in 18th Century America", 1946-1947 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - "Painting in 19th Century Europe" (Lecture I-III), 1937 (Box 12, Folder 2-4)
  - "Painting in 19th Century Europe" (Lecture IV-VI), 1937 (Box 12, Folder 5-7)
  - "Place of Art in Education", 1935 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - "Place of Art in Social Life", circa 1920-1960 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - "Pre-Raphaelites", 1946 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - "Present Position of German Museums", 1950 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - "Problems and Possessions of American Art Galleries", 1957 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - "Relations of American and British 18th Century Art", circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - "Review of Friedlander's David to Delacroix", 1953 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - "Richard Wilson", circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - "Rubens, up to 1630", circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - "Rubens, 1630-1940; Van Dyke", circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - "Sienese and Gothic Influence in Florence and Northern Italy", circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - "Sienese Painting, 14th and 15th Centuries", circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - "Social Necessity of Art", 1942-1943 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - "Some Masterpieces of the Boston Museum", 1942, 1957 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - "Sometimes a Miracle Happens", circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - "Spanish 17th Century Painting", circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - "Spanish Painting", circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - "Spiritual Problems of an Artist", 1945 (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - "Sport and Art", circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - "Still Life Painting Since 1470," Cincinnati Art Museum, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - "Typographical Tradition in 18th Century Italy," Athenaeum, circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - "Twenty Years of Study in Renaissance History of Art", 1959 (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - "Two Canalettos", circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - "Velasquez and 17th Century Spanish Painting", 1947 (Box 12, Folder 31)
  - "Velasquez and the School of Madrid", circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 32)
  - "Venetian 18th Century Painting", 1948 (Box 12, Folder 33)
  - "Venetian Painters in England in the 18th Century", circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 34)
  - "Venice and England in the 18th Century", circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 35)
  - "Visitor to Venice", circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 36)
  - "Visual Arts", 1955 (Box 12, Folder 38)
  - "Visual Arts as an Aspect of the Human Spirit," Columbia University, 1953, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 37)
  - "Where Do We Go From Here? Or Museum Problems in a Changing World", 1955 (Box 12, Folder 39)
  - "Whistler," Nottingham University, 1934 (Box 12, Folder 40)
  - "Why Waste Money on Art Galleries?", 1938 (Box 12, Folder 41)
  - "William Hogarth", circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 42)
  - "William Morris", circa 1930-1950 (Box 12, Folder 43)
  - "Works of Art in Wartime", 1944 (Box 12, Folder 44)
- Writings and Notes, 1910-1974; Series 4; 2 Linear feet Box 13-14
  Writings consist of Constable's published articles on art, exhibition catalog introductions, and articles submitted for the Encyclopedia of World Art. Essay drafts include writings and translations from Constable's early university years, in addition to later essays that touch on concerns of museum curatorship. The series also includes miscellaneous writing notes, bibliographies, and drafts and research material related to Art Collecting in the United States, Art History and Connoisseurship, and The Painter's Workshop.
  Materials retain their original order within each folder.
  - Articles, circa 1910-1960 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Articles, 1914-1930 (Box 13, Folder 2-6)
  - Articles, 1931-1939 (Box 13, Folder 7-10)
  - Articles, 1940-1949 (Box 13, Folder 11-15)
  - Articles, 1950-1974 (Box 13, Folder 16-20)
  - Articles, Encyclopedia of World Art, circa 1956-1966 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Articles, Encyclopedia of World Art, 1956-1959 (Box 13, Folder 22-26)
  - Articles, Encyclopedia of World Art, 1960-1966 (Box 13, Folder 27-28)
  - Booklets, 1930-1956 (Box 13, Folder 29)
  - Book, Art Collecting in the United States (research), 1958-1964 (Box 13, Folder 30-33)
  - Book, Art Collecting in the United States (notes), 1958-1961 (Box 13, Folder 34-37)
  - Book, Art History and Connoisseurship, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 38)
  - Book, Painter's Workshop (correspondence), 1947-1966 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Book, Painter's Workshop (printer's draft), 1953 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Book, Painter's Workshop (clippings), 1954 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Book, Painter's Workshop (research), 1947-1953 (Box 14, Folder 4-8)
  - Handbook on the Preservation of Paintings, 1930-1936 (Box 14, Folder 9-13)
  - Translation, "Relations with the German Art Group", circa 1905-1920 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Translation, "The Problem of England", circa 1905-1920 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Unpublished Essay, "Present Economic and Political Forces", 1910 (Box 14, Folder 16-17)
  - Unpublished Essay, "State Intervention in Industrial Disputes", circa 1910-1920 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Unpublished Poem, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Draft, "Cares of a Curator", circa 1920-1950 (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Draft, [Charitable Contributions to Museums], circa 1920-1950 (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Draft, "Eric Brown as I Knew Him", circa 1920-1950 (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Draft, [Exhibition and Book Introduction], circa 1920-1950 (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Draft, "Gothic Art", circa 1920-1950 (Box 14, Folder 24-26)
  - Draft, "Modern War", circa 1920-1950 (Box 14, Folder 27)
  - Draft, "Veneitan Painting", circa 1920-1950 (Box 14, Folder 28)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1930-1962 (Box 14, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous Writing Notes, circa 1920-1950 (Box 14, Folder 30-31)
  - Bibliographies, circa 1920-1950 (Box 14, Folder 32-33)
- American Defense Harvard Group, 1942-1946; Series 5; 0.6 Linear feet Box 15
  American Defense Harvard Group includes materials related to Constable's advisory work in drafting and organizing lists of men with curatorial, museum conservation, or library/archives backgrounds to aid in the identification, protection, and restoration of cultural artifacts during World War II. Correspondence with Ralph Perry, Paul Sachs, George Stout, and Hugh Hencken document the rationale for forming the Harvard Group, trace the formation of its goals and objectives, and includes many of the original lists that were generated and forwarded to the Commission for the Protection and Salvage of Artistic and Historic Monuments in Europe, also known as the Roberts Commission. The series also includes the Harvard Group's manual Safeguarding and Conserving Cultural Materials in the Field, committee minutes and reports, and clippings related to their work.
  Materials are arranged chronologically within each folder.
  - A Miscellaneous, 1945 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - American Institute of Architects, 1943 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - American Museum of Natural History (Murphy, Robert C.), 1943-1944 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - B Miscellaneous, 1943 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - British Embassy (Nicoll, Allardyce), 1943-1944 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - C Miscellaneous, 1943-1944 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Commission for the Protection and Salvage of Artistic and Historic Monuments in Europe, 1943-1946 (Box 15, Folder 7-9)
    Robert's Commission established by President Roosevelt
  - D-H Miscellaneous, 1943-1944 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Harvard University, American Defense Harvard Group (Perry, Ralph), 1943-1944 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Harvard University, Fogg Museum of Art (Sachs, Paul and Stout, George), 1942-1946 (Box 15, Folder 12-14)
  - Harvard University, Peabody Museum (Hencken, Hugh), 1943 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - I-M Miscellaneous, 1943-1944 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art (Pease, Murray), 1943-1944 (Box 15, Folder 17)